Professor Voronov’s talk and Shri Mataji’s acceptance of the award, Turkey, 1994
Professor Voronov’un Konuşması ve Shri Mataji’nin ödülü kabulü
Simultaneous translation of professor Voronov from a Russian Sahaja Yogi.
Profesor Voronov'un konuşmasını Rus Sahaja Yogi çeviriyor.
Morality and knowledge, these are two things which
Ahlak ve bilgi, bunlar tüm dünyayı
make the whole world think award.
üzerinde düşündüren iki şey.
There are wars now on the planet and civil wars,
Şimdilerde, gezegende savaşlar var,
the blood of human beings is shed.
iç savaşlar var, insan kanı dökülüyor. Ve bu dönemde
Our scientist, by my initiative,
Bilim adamlarımız, benim girişimim üzerine
unanimously elected our holy Mother, Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi,
oybirliğiyle, Kutsal Annemiz Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi’yi
an honorary member of our Academy.
Akademimizin onursal üyesi seçtiler.
The last time, in Moscow,
Geçen sefer, Moskova’da,
we hand it over to our holy Mother a diploma
Kendisini  seven Sahaja Yogiler tarafından
made by Sahaja Yogis, loving Sahaja Yogis.
hazırlanmış bir diplomayı, Kutsal Annemize teslim ettik.
Now, this is a diploma of the Government of Russia.
Şimdi, bu Rusya Hükümeti’nin bir diplomasıdır..
I would like to say a few words about what is actually this Academy, and who is a member of it.
Bu Akademinin gerçekte ne olduğu ve üyelerinin kimler olduğu hakkında birkaç şey söylemek istiyorum.
There are members, among the members we have painters, scientists,
Üyelerimiz var, üyelerimiz arasında ressamlar, bilim adamları,
musicians of different directions.
farklı alanlarda çalışan müzisyenler var,
But we have also honorary members of our Academy,
Akademimizin fahri üyeleri de var
but they are very few in number.
ama onların sayısı çok az.
One is Antonio Juan Samaranch
Bunlardan birisi, Antonio Juan Samaranch
who is the president of the Olympic Committee of the world.
Dünya Olimpiyat Komitesi Başkanı.
Two or three Ministers who, in their own countries,
Kendi ülkelerinde, kendi ülkelerindeki halkın içinde
liquidated the illiteracy in the population of their country.
cehaleti ortadan kaldıran iki veya üç tane Bakan. Hepsi de erkek.
Shri Mataji is the only lady on the world
Shri Mataji, bu Akademinin
who has been elected an honorary member of this Academy.
onursal üyesi seçilen dünyadaki tek hanımefendidir.
I have to say a lot.
Çok şey söylemek zorundayım.
I know that here we have the best representatives of the nations of the world.
Burada dünya milletlerinin en iyi temsilcilerine sahip olduğumuzu biliyorum
But there are some exceptions.
ama bazı istisnalar var.
We have to put our love first to our self-perfection, self-cognition,
Sevgimizi önce kendi mükemmelliğimize, kendimizi tanımaya vermeliyiz,
to put our, first, the love to our countries.
sevgimizi öncelikle kendi ülkelerimize vermeliyiz.
We need that only to do helping that victorious
Kutsal Annemizin muzaffer ideallerinin
victorious ideals of our holy Mother should not have any hindrance at all
hiçbir şekilde engellenmemesi için her şeyi yapmalıyız.
into that, we should self-perfect ourselves.
Bunun için de kendimizi mükemmelleştirmeliyiz.
Yes, we do have something negative besides the positive things.
Evet, bizde olumlu olan şeyler yanında, olumsuz şeyler de var.
For example, me and also our Sahaja Yogis from Turkey,
Mesela ben ve Türkiyeli Sahaja Yogilerimiz,
they can see how the pieces of bread are spread on the floor.
ekmek parçalarının nasıl yerlere atıldığını görebilirler.
It’s very bad, I consider it very bad.
Bu çok kötü, ben bunu çok kötü bir şey olarak değerlendiriyorum.
My daughter by name Svetlana, she is also Sahaja Yogi,
Kızım Svetlana, o da bir Sahaja Yogi
she said,
ve bana dedi ki,
“I’ve been living for a long time among the Muslims and I know their attitude towards bread.
“uzun zamandır Müslümanlar arasında yaşıyorum ve onların ekmeğe karşı gösterdikleri tutumlarını biliyorum.
If a piece of bread has been falling on earth,
Eğer yere bir parça ekmek düşmüşse,
then they pick it up, they kiss it and put
onu yerden alıp öper ve
it somewhere for the birds to pick it up”.
kuşların alması için ekmeği (yüksek) bir yere koyarlar”, dedi.
We also have to feel respect
Ekmeği üreten bu emekçilere,
to the laborious people who are producing this bread, to peasants.
köylülere de saygı duymak zorundayız.
I address to all the Sahaja Yogis who are working in the press media,
Basında çalışan, gazetecilik yapan bütün Sahaja Yogilere sesleniyorum:
who are journalists: we need to disseminate
Kutsal Annemizin fikirlerini bizler her yerde,
the ideas of our holy Mother everywhere, on press, television and magazines.
basında, televizyonda ve dergilerde yaymalıyız.
If we do so and behave properly, we can be a real example,
Eğer bunu yapar ve düzgün davranırsak,
we can make real examples for the nations of the whole world.
gerçek birer örnek olabiliriz, tüm dünya uluslarına gerçek örnekler teşkil edebiliriz
But maybe, today, they started to call Sahaja Yogis
ama belki bugün belki de onlar, bundan pek de memnun olmayanlara
who were not perhaps quite satisfied with it.
Sahaja Yogi demeye başladılar.
Still, we have to make it better.
Yine de, bizler bu durumu daha iyi bir hale getirmeliyiz.
Taking into account an energetic activity of Shri Mataji,
Shri Mataji’nin enerjik aktivitesini göz önüne aldığımızda,
it gives us an idea to propose to elect Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi,
bu durum bize Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi’yi
a laureate of the Noble Price winner for peace.
Nobel Barış ödülü için teklif etme fikrini verdi.
For that purpose, we have to work hard in our own countries
Bu amaçla, Shri Mataji’nin fikirlerinin hakikaten gerçekleşmesi
for Shri Mataji’s ideas to be really realized,
ve bilinç seviyesinin ötesinde anlaşılması için
understood beyond the level of consciousness.
kendi ülkelerimizde çok çalışmalıyız.
To reach that level for the Noble Price,
Nobel  Barış ödülü seviyesine ulaşmak için,
we need to make an example, we need to make the society,
bizler birer örnek teşkil etmeliyiz, toplumun,
the publicity, press, to realize the ideas of Shri Mataji,
yayıncıların, basının, Shri Mataji’nin fikirlerinin,
how beneficial they are for the whole humanity.
tüm insanlık için ne kadar yararlı olduğunu fark etmelerini sağlamalıyız.
In Petroski Academy of Arts and Science,
birçok seçkin insan var ve belki de
we have many outstanding people and perhaps
Nirmala Yoga dergisinde
we shall publish a special article for that in Nirmala Yoga magazine.
bu konuda özel bir makale yayınlarız.
But, with all my heart and in the name of all members of
Ama tüm kalbimle ve Sanat
the Academy of Arts and Science,
ve Bilim Akademisinin tüm üyeleri adına,
I would like to make a sort of present to Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi.
Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi’ye bir tür hediye sunmak istiyorum.
This is a reproduction of Dona Latte,
Bu Dona Latte’nın bir reprodüksiyonu,
it’s a – [aside] sorry, sorry, no, no, Mona Lisa is different.
bu – [yan tarafa doğru konuşuyor] üzgünüm, üzgünüm, hayır, hayır, Mona Lisa farklı.
It’s Dona Latte,
Bu, Leonardo Da Vinci’den Dona Latte,
which you can find in State Hermitage by Leonardo.
Madonna, St Petersburg’daki Hermitaj Devlet müzesinde görebilirsiniz.
(Madonna del Latte) It’s different.
(Leonardo Da Vinci’nin Madonna del Latte) –Bu farklı.
And the last.
Ve son olarak,
We have really to watch our own behaviour, not to do any negative things.
bizler gerçekten kendi davranışlarımızı gözlemeli, olumsuz şeyler yapmamalıyız.
For our compatriots in all our countries would say
Çünkü tüm ülkelerde yurttaşlarımız, “Bir Sahaja Yogi,
that, “Sahaja Yogi is really the best representative of humanity in all the countries”.
gerçekten bütün ülkelerde, insanlığın en iyi temsilcileri” demeli.
That is our purpose.
Amacımız budur.
I don't know, but
Bilemiyorum
how to say
ama Rus alimleri
as to the Russian scholars and scientists.
ve bilim adamları için ne demeli.
Scientists are amoral people because science is immoral.
Bilim adamları ahlaksız insanlardır çünkü bilim ahlaksızdır.
But I was surprised that in Leningrad [St Petersburg],
Ama Leningrad’da [St Petersburg], profesörün sayesinde,
thanks to professor, we had about two thousand scientists –
Beni bu kadar onurlandıran yaklaşık iki bin –
I don’t know, ten thousand probably –
bilmiyorum, muhtemelen on bin tane –
who honoured Me so much.
bilim adamımızın olmasına şaşırdım.
And I told about one centre only there, that is Swadishthan.
Ve orada Ben sadece tek bir merkezden bahsettim, o da Swadishthana.
How Swadishthan they are ruing your life.
Swadhisthana hayatınızı nasıl mahvediyor.
And they were listening to Me, absolutely, with the right attention.
Ve onlar Beni kesinlikle, doğru bir dikkatle dinliyorlardı.
All right.
Pekala.
Very surprisingly, I’ve never seen such scientists,
Çok şaşırtıcı bir şekilde, Ben hiç böyle bilim adamları görmedim
because they cannot see something beyond science
çünkü bilim insanları, bilimin ötesini göremezler
and Sahaja Yoga is meta science,
ve Sahaja Yoga meta bilimdir,
it is beyond science.
o bilimin ötesindedir.
And when I told them how so many diseases
Ve onlara bu kadar çok hastalığın
are caused by one centre,
tek bir çakradan kaynaklandığını söylediğimde,
they were really amazed at it.
buna gerçekten şaşırdılar.
But they were open, open-minded people
Ama onlar açık, çok açık fikirli insanlardı
and a scientist means an open-minded person.
ve bir bilim adamı, açık fikirli bir insan anlamına gelir.
I was amazed also, the way they gave Me awards.
Bana ödül verme şekillerine de hayran kaldım.
The first award when they gave Me,
İlk ödülü Bana verdiklerinde,
I said, “What is this?
Ben “Nedir bu? dedim.
I’m the tenth member of such an old university where
Şimdi, çok, çok büyük bilim adamlarının bu ödülü aldığı,
very, very great scientists have got this award.
eski bir üniversitenin, onuncu üyesiyim.
So, how can you give Me such a honour?”
Yani Bana böyle bir onuru siz nasıl bahşedebilirsiniz ki?
So, professor Voronov told Me that, “Mother
Bunun üzerine Profesör Voronov Bana dedi ki, “Anne
these scientists have only worked with matter.
bu bilim adamları sadece madde ile çalıştılar
But you have worked with human beings and transformed them”.
ama siz insanlarla çalıştınız ve onları dönüştürdünüz”.
I was surprised the way he saw the point.
Onun konuya gösterdiği bu bakış açısına şaşırdım.
It’s not easy to see this point
Günümüzde insanın dönüşümünün,
that transformation of human beings is most important today.
en önemli şey olduğu noktasını görmek kolay bir şey değildir.
If I have achieved it, it’s nothing great, I think,
Eğer bunu Ben başardıysam, bunda olağanüstü olan bir şey yok
because I knew how to do it. So, it’s nothing great.
çünkü bunu nasıl yapacağımı Ben biliyordum.
But I really feel very proud of you
Ama siz bunu başardığınız için, sizlerle
that you have achieved it. I have not achieved anything.
gerçekten gurur duyuyorum. Ben hiçbir şey elde etmedim.
I was born like this.
Ben bu şekilde doğdum
But you have achieved it.
ama sizler bunu başardınız.
So many nations here sitting,
Pek çok ulus burada oturuyor,
enjoying the same beautiful feeling of your Spirit.
Ruhunuzun aynı güzel hissiyatının tadını çıkarıyorsunuz.
And they are from different nations, different places, different religions,
Ve onlar farklı milletlerden, farklı yerlerden, farklı dinlerden
and genuinely they are feeling the joy of their Spirit.
ve onlar sahiden de Ruhlarının sevincini hissediyorlar.
And this is something, was my dream and vision.
Ve bu, Benim hayalim ve vizyonum olan bir şey
But I never thought of Noble Price or anything like that.
ama Nobel  ödülü ya da onun gibi bir şeyi hiç düşünmedim.
Because, my husband has got all kind of prizes
Because, my husband has got all kind of prizes
and he always, says, “All due to my wife”.
Çünkü kocamın her türden ödülü var ve der ki bunlar “Eşim sayesinde”.
But what I really treasure is this,
Ama Benim gerçekten değer verdiğim şey şu,
that in a great country like Russia where
bilimin doruklara ulaştığı Rusya gibi büyük bir ülkede,
science has reached its heights,
Beni büyük bir bilim adamı
that they should accept Me
ve akademisyen olarak kabul etmeleri,
is something really very remarkable,
gerçekten çok dikkate değer bir şey
though I don’t know if I deserve it or not.
ve bunu hak edip etmediğimi bilmiyorum
But that’s what they feel about it.
ama onların bu konuda hissettikleri şey bu.
Professor Voronov: There’s no doubt about it.
Profesör Voronov: Buna hiç şüphe yok.
Moreover, all the false gurus are banned in Russia.
Üstelik Rusya’da tüm sahte gurular yasaklanmıştır
But I was surprised also that they did not ban us.
ama bize yasaklama getirmemelerine şaşırdım.
Apart from that, the patriarch,
Bunun dışında patrik,
who is like a pope of Leningrad of the white order,
beyaz düzenin Leningrad papası gibi bir şey
he himself invited me to be there.
Beni oraya kendisi davet etti.
So, we are entering into the realm of religion also.
Bu sayede biz din alanına da girmiş oluyoruz.
It’s something – not only science,
Bu, sadece bilim değil, aynı zamanda,
but also religion which is,
onların gözlerini açıp
which has to open eyes and see
neleri kaçırdıklarını görmeleri gereken din,
all the promises that the Prophets gave,
Peygamberlerin, enkarnasyonların
that the incarnations gave are to be fulfilled.
tüm vaatlerinin yerine gelmesidir.
If they can just see this point,
Eğer onlar sadece bu noktayı görebilseler,
it will be so great. I was surprised also
bu çok harika olacak. Patrik’in, bu konferansa
that patriarch himself invites Me to this conference.
Beni de davet etmesine şaşırdım.
So, two great things, I feel,
Yani, iki tane harika şey var, hissediyorum ki,
that not only in science but also in religion,
sadece bilimde değil, dinde de,
Sahaja Yoga is entering and will remove the darkness of ignorance.
Sahaja Yoga dahil oluyor ve bu cehaletin karanlığını ortadan kaldıracaktır.
Another thing I must tell you that when I went to Brasilia
Söylemek zorunda olduğum başka bir şey de şu ki, başkenti Brezilya olan
which is the capital of Brazil, the Mayor of Brasilia
Brezilya’ya gittiğimde, başkent olan Brezilya’nın Belediye Başkanı
came to receive Me and he gave Me the keys of Brasilia
Beni almaya geldi ve “Anne, lütfen Brezilya’ya iyi bakın” diyerek
saying, “Mother, please look after Brazil”. I was really amazed.
başkent Brezilya’nın anahtarlarını Bana verdi. Buna gerçekten şaşırdım.
So, on the political side also, if we start entering into,
Yani siyasi tarafta da, eğer biz içine girmeye başlarsak
our problems should be solved.
sorunlarımız çözülmelidir.
We should have no problems,
Hiçbir sorunumuz olmamalı,
we should have no quarrels, no fights, nothing.
hiçbir kavgamız, dövüşümüz, hiçbir şeyimiz olmamalıdır.
But let us live with happiness and joy.
Mutluluk ve neşe içinde yaşayalım.
I’m sure with this [award],
Bu [ödül] sayesinde
I can see that vision coming through.
bu vizyonun ortaya çıktığını görebiliyorum.
This vision of mine
Benim vizyonum,
of seeing the whole world in peace and joy enjoying themselves.
tüm dünyayı huzur ve neşe içinde, eğlenirken görmektir.
All of you, as he said, have to help Me,
Hepiniz, Voronov’un da dediği gibi, Bana yardım etmeli
have to come up as real great Sahaja Yogis.
ve gerçek büyük Sahaja Yogiler olarak ortaya çıkmalısınız.
I don’t know Sir, how to thank you very much
Bilemiyorum efendim, size nasıl teşekkür edeceğimi bilemiyorum
because I have no words.
çünkü söyleyecek bir söz bulamıyorum
But he has been meeting Me for three, four years and
ama kendisi üç, dört yıldır Benimle tanışıyor
I was surprised, he is such a learned man,
ve Ben hayret ettim, kendisi çok bilgili bir adam,
such an educated person,
böylesine eğitimli bir insan,
and how he could see the subtle side of life!
hayatın inceliklerini nasıl görebiliyor!
And that they discussed about morality!
Ve onların ahlak üzerine tartışmaları!
All the time, all the subject was that of morality.
Sürekli olarak, konu tamamen ahlaktı.
There was a gentleman who was a surgeon  who is –
Cerrah olan bir bey vardı –
How old is he? Eighty years.
Kaç yaşında? Seksen yaşında mı.
Sahaja Yogi: Ninety-three.
Sahaja Yogi: Doksan üç.
Very old,
Çok yaşlı
but he is still doing operations.
ama hala ameliyat yapıyor.
He is still doing operations
Halen ameliyat yapıyor
and he is the one who wrote against alcohol.
ve alkole karşı yazılar yazan da o.
And I was really surprised.
Ve Ben buna gerçekten şaşırdım.
Professor Voronov:  Fyodor Uglov.
Profesör Voronov:  Fyodor Uglov.
Professor Voronov: Academician Uglov.
Profesör Voronov: Akademisyen  Uglov.
He wrote a book against alcohol
Votka’nın bu kadar yaygın olduğu bir ülkede,
in a country where Vodka is so common.
o alkole karşı bir kitap yazdı
But just imagine!
ama sadece bir düşünün!
And these people listen to their elders.
Ve bu insanlar büyüklerini dinlerler.
They are not like Western people
Onlar büyüklerine değer vermeyen
who do not care for their elders.
Batılılar gibi değiller.
They listen to their elders who are very wise.
Çok bilge olan büyüklerini dinlerler.
One day, I’m sure, Russia will be
Bir gün eminim ki Rusya en önemli,
one of the most important religious country.
dini bütün ülkelerden birisi olacak.
It will have such a big name one day
Bir gün çok büyük bir ismi olacak
because they have taken to truth and not to some nonsensical things.
çünkü onlar saçma sapan şeylere değil, gerçeğe yöneldiler.
And I am sure this will prove to the whole world
Ve eminim ki bu, tüm dünyaya,
that truth is what we should ask for.
gerçeğin istememiz gereken şey olduğunu kanıtlayacaktır.
We should not get
Hiçbir şekilde yalanın egemenliğine girmemeliyiz
because untruth will never bring joy or peace.
çünkü gerçek olmayan asla neşe veya barış getirmeyecektir.
Actually, I am overwhelmed by what he has said
Aslında, onun söyledikleri Beni çok etkiledi
and I’m happy he has made you so happy also
ve hakkımda bu güzel şeyleri söyleyerek sizi de
by saying these beautiful things about Me.
bu kadar mutlu ettiği için mutluyum
But I must tell you, I’m a very humble housewife.
ama size söylemeliyim ki Ben çok mütevazı bir ev hanımıyım.
That’s all I am.
Olduğum şey bu
But if you think I’m more than that, I’m not going to challenge it.
ama eğer siz Benim bundan daha fazlası olduğumu düşünüyorsanız da, buna karşı çıkmayacağım.
Now we have to thank the Turkish people, the French people,
Şimdi tüm sorunlara rağmen bu güzel programı
for organizing this beautiful program
ve bu evlilikleri organize eden Türklere,
and these weddings, despite all the problems.
Fransızlara teşekkür etmeliyiz.
And also, to every way,
Ayrıca, her şekilde çok çalışın
work so hard because there were only forty Sahaja Yogis in Turkey
çünkü Türkiye’de sadece kırk tane Sahaja Yogi vardı
and they have done such a dedicated work.
ve onlar çok özverili bir iş yaptılar.
And so capable they are!
Ve o kadar becerikliler!
I’m amazed to see this kind of industrious,
Bu tür çalışkan, ya da demeliyim ki, çok çalışkan,
I should say, or very hard-working people, very hard working.
çok çalışkan insanlar görmek Beni şaşırttı.
And all the problems are solved here,
Ve burada tüm sorunlar çözüldü
they say, “Mother, you have solved all of the problems.”
ve onlar “Anne, tüm sorunları Siz  çözdünüz” diyorlar.
Now I would say the marriages have been done very gracefully.
Şimdi, evliliklerin de çok zarif bir şekilde yapıldığını söyleyebilirim.
Now, don’t spoil your marriages and create problems for Me.
Şimdi, evliliklerinizi bozmayın ve Bana sorun yaratmayın.
That’s all I want to know that you’ll have very nice children,
Tek bilmek istediğim şey, çok güzel çocuklarınızın olacağı,
and that you create a society and help the society
sizlerin bir toplum yaratacağınız ve büyük barış yapıcıların toplumuna
of great peacemakers.
yardım edeceğinizdir.
Thank you very much.
Çok teşekkürler.
Thank you
Teşekkür ederim.